本影音版权属其出版、发行方，字幕制作仅供学术交流之用 请于下载后24小时内删除，并不得有公开传播或作商业盈利之行为 若有违法等相关行为，诸神字幕组恕不承担任何法律或连带责任。
翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
私には見える　明日が見える
I can see it. I can see tomorrow.
The countless tomorrows of
countless struggling souls...
この世に蠢く無数の人々の　無数の明日が
Some of them sad,
悲しむ者　苦しむ者　喜ぶ者
some of them in pain,
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
and some of them joyful.
Their tales continue to progress,
物語が紡がれていく
until the tale of the world
itself comes to an end.
世界という名の物語が終わる その時まで
止まる者　愚かなりし
Todomaru mono oroka narishi
はらりひらり指に触れた黒い翼の　一片
Harari hirari yubi ni fureta
kuroi tsubasa no hitohira
诸
神&动漫国
君が一つの　物語なら
Kimi ga hitotsu no monogatari nara
まだいくらでも　掛け替えられる
Mada ikura demo kakikaerareru
血のインクは乾かない
Chi no inku wa kawakanai
誰も知らない　本との僕ら
Dare mo shiranai hontou no bokura
荒れた世界　枯れるのは
Areta sekai kaeru no wa
追い求めたのは　ちっぽけな幸福なんかじゃない
Oimotometa no wa
Chippoke na koufuku nanka ja nai
戦え　轟く　音を合図に
Tatakae todoroku kodou wo aizu ni
意のまま　進めば
Inomama susumeba yukusaki hatenai
行く先　果てない
抗え　のたうち
Aragae notauchi ikudo to yaburedo
幾度と　汚れと
Kizamou matotta kizuato ni yume wo
膝を纏った傷跡に夢を
埋もれそうな今日の記憶繋げるために　明日へ
Umoresou na kyo no kioku
tsunageru tame ni ashita e
Episode 14
The Setting Sun, a Storyteller, and a Collection of Fables
第14话 落日
与
往事
和
数个寓言
Long, long ago,
遥か昔　「始まりと終わりの管理者」が現れ
a being known as the Overseer of the
Alpha and the Omega appeared.
混沌から天と地と海を作りました
He created the Heavens, the Earth,
and the oceans from chaos.
次に　残った混沌を固めて削り
Then he molded and shaped the animals
and plants from the remaining chaos.
動物と植物を
He then created mankind from
the final remaining chaos.
残った混沌を加工して人間を
Last, he divided his own
body into thirds
最後に自分の体を切り裂いて　三人の神を作りました
and created three deities.
The overseer of life that is
yet to come, Orntorra.
未だ来らざる者の管理者＝オルントーラ
The overseer of life that
now exists, Towitorra.
現れある者の管理者＝トーイトーラ
過ぎ去りし者の管理者＝バントーラ
The overseer of life that
has passed, Bantorra.
has passed, Bantorra,
過ぎ去りし者の管理者＝バントーラは図書館を作りました
built a Library.
The souls of humans, who have passed on,
return to the earth and fossilize.
死んだ人間の魂は土に帰り　化石となる
その化石は「本」と呼ばれ
These fossils are known as "Books."
Touching one allows you to read
the memories of its owner.
触れると死んだ者の記憶を読むことができました
These Books are brought to the Library.
「本」を図書館に集められて
A group of humans has been
entrusted to watch over them.
その管理は人間に委ねられました
Well now...
さーて　始まり始まり
And so it begins.
The Books' guardians, chosen by the
God of the Past, Bantorra...
過去神バントーラに選ばれし　「本」の守護者たち
どうした？
What just happened?
The Books' guardians, chosen by the
God of the Past, Bantorra...
Is it Armed Librarians?
武装司書か？
They do say that the Armed Librarian
is the most difficult of
世界で一番就くのが難しい職業　それが武装司書だと言われています
all the world's vocations to enter.
To defeat the monsters lurking in
the labyrinth beneath the annals
収蔵庫の地下迷宮に巣くう魔物たちを倒し
「本」を管理できる強さを持つ
and have the strength to
oversee the Books.
These are the absolute requirements
for an Armed Librarian.
それが武装司書の絶対条件
And the one who currently
stands above us all...
そして現在　我々の頂点に立つのが…
Acting Director Hamyuts Meseta, yes?
ハミュッツ＝メセタ　館長代行ね
No one can deny that she's strong,
確かにあの人は強い　ですが…
but...
But?
ですが？
Never mind.
いいえ
All those inhuman deeds committed by you,
the Church of Drowning in God's Grace,
神溺教団
あらゆる非人道的行為を行い
you heretics who have decried
the value of love...
あらゆる愛を無価値とする邪教
You're the ones who aren't human!
お前たちは人間じゃない
奪い　踏み躙る者
There are those who steal from
and trample upon others.
There are those who are robbed and trampled.
奪われ　踏み躙られる者
全てを失う者
There are those who have lost everything.
生を　思いを　絆を
Life, thought, bonds with others...
ハミュッツ＝メセタを…殺せ
Kill...
Hamyuts Meseta!
And love.
そして　愛を
All humans are born into
this world to be loved.
全ての人間は愛されるために生まれてきたから
To love and be loved...
To experience fulfillment, never suffering...
愛し　愛され　満ち足り　苦しむことなく
To live a life in utmost bliss...
至上の幸福に包まれた一生を送るために
Then let me ask you this, Colio Tonies:
では　コリオ＝トニス
Why do you do that which you do?
なぜお前はそうしている？
コリオ＝トニスは人間ではない
Colio Tonies is not human.
コリオ＝トニスは爆弾だ
Colio Tonies is a bomb.
待って　君は助かりたくないのか？
Wait! Don't you want to be rescued?
Why? Why are you just giving up?!
なぜだ　なぜ助かろうとしない？
You just have to grab my hand...
この手を掴めば…
Don't you want to survive?!
生きたくないのか？
I shall become a Book greater than
all others and ascend into Heaven.
私は誰よりも優れた「本」となり
天国へと召し上げられる
I shall have more pages than any other of you,
with the most lustrous spine ever seen!
お前たちの誰よりも分厚く
誰よりも輝く背表紙
誰よりも幸福な物語を紡ぐ
I shall write the greatest tale
of happiness ever told!
Whose Book is it? Where did you get it?
誰の「本」　どこで手に入れた？
There are those who dream of having
the most beautiful book in the world.
夢に焦がれし者　それはこの世で最も美しい「本」
No matter. It's a far too
sophisticated toy for Meat.
There are those who dream of having
the most beautiful book in the world.
まぁ　いい　「肉」には過ぎたおもちゃではあるが
Dead humans become books.
死んだ人間は「本」になる
Though the pages in yours will be blank...
だが　お前の「本」は余白だらけだろうな
We are of the heretic creed,
武装司書が全力を挙げて取り締まっている禁断の邪教
that which the Armed Librarians devote
full efforts toward stopping...
それが我々
神溺教団
The Church of Drowning in God's Grace.
Precisely.
その通り　我々の教義はただ一つ
Our doctrine espouses but one directive,
to actualize your every desire.
己の欲望をすべて肯定すること
Desire?
欲望？
Food, sex, fame...
食欲　色欲　名誉欲　支配欲に破壊欲
The desire to rule and the
desire to destroy...
And only those who embody the true
happiness found by fulfilling their desires
己が欲望を突き詰め　真の幸福を体現した者だけが
will, upon death, be granted
entrance into Heaven.
死後天国に迎え入れられる
They will become the ultimate books.
究極の幸福な「本」となって
I see sadness in your eyes.
悲しい目をしているね
Huh?
え？
I'll help you forget about it.
忘れさせてあげよ
This medicine will make you happy.
幸福になれる薬さ
I need it only for myself.
私だけでいい
I, alone, will become the most beautiful
Book this world has ever seen!
私だけがこの世でただ一冊の美しい「本」となるのだ
I don't need a child that balks
at the sight of dying Meats.
「肉」どもの死に動揺するような子どもはお断り
You're strong.
強さはある　知性も　適性も
You're smart and talented.
But you
けど　あなたには…心がない
don't have a heart!
Books drift from person to person.
「本」は人から人へ　曲がれ　漂う
Hey, guys! Interested in Books?
Books drift from person to person.
お兄さんたち　「本」に興味がないかい？
What about Book central, Toatt Mine?
「本」の名産地トアット土産に　どうだ？
Just yesterday, they dug
these out of the mine.
昨日掘り出したばっかりの「本」だ
They're all top-quality, sealed rarities.
どれもこれも超一級封印ものの貴重品だ
Let's go.
行くぞ
Ah, hold on!
よっ　待ちなぁよ
砕けた欠片ちょっとしか読めんねえが
I've got a broken fragment,
so you can only read a bit of it.
Since it's incomplete, I'll cut you a deal.
その分　安くしっとくぜ
Shlamuffen...
シュラムッフェン
Hamyuts Meseta,
ハミュッツ＝メセタ
君には僕の「本」の帯になってもらおう
you will become the slogan
on my Book's cover.
It shall be written as follows:
帯にはこう書かれる
The joy of killing the strongest
Armed Librarian, Hamyuts Meseta.
最強の武装司書　ハミュッツ＝メセタを倒す幸福っと
Ever-laughing magic blade, Shlamuffen!
「常笑いの魔刀」シュラムッフェン
シロン　人間は素晴らしいものだ
Shiron... Humans are wondrous beings.
I have to go.
行かなきゃ
どこに？
Where?
I don't know.
分からない　多分戦うんだと思う
Probably to fight.
Fight who?
誰と？
分からない　けど…
I don't know. But...
Thank you. I owe everything to you.
ありがとう　全部君のおかげだ
I'm not sure I follow,
よく分からないけど
カートヘロのおかげって言ってくれたほうが
but I'll be happy if you thank Carthelo instead.
あたしは嬉しいな
It's thanks to you and Carthelo.
イアとカートヘロのおかげだ
まさか　こんな所で
Never in my wildest dreams did I think
you'd get the upper hand on me.
こんなくそを追い詰められるとはね
You're...
お前？
A Meat?
「肉」
Why did you come here?
何しに来たの？
To fight!
戦う
ふん！　肉がそれで僕に勝とうというのか？
A Meat thinks it can defeat me with that?
Are you an idiot?
あんた　バカ？
分からない
I don't know.
How do you plan on winning?
どうやって勝つつもり？
I don't know!
分からない
Beat it, then.
じゃ　消えな
No! I'm fighting!
いや　戦う
なぜ？
Why?
あの人が見たのは逃げる僕じゃない
She didn't see me running away!
She saw me fighting!
戦う僕だから
「真人」の「本」にしては　いささかお粗末でしたな
This is somewhat unimpressive for
the Book of a True Man.
One cannot strive to create a quality Book
and merely expect it to come into being,
優れた「本」というのは求めて与えられるものではないのだよ
for God is hallowed,
and Heaven is a far-off place.
それだけに神は尊く　天国は遠い
I wouldn't want to end up such a Book as this.
なりたくないものですなあ　このような「本」には
Once again, I can't save anyone?
俺はまた誰も救えないのか？
何者だ？
Who's there?!
It appears there's no one here better suited
to pick this story up from where it leaves off,
この途切れた物語を継ぐのに相応しい御方は
あなたのほかにはいらっしゃらないようです
Master Volken.
ヴォルケン様
Volken did it?
ヴォルケンが？
They're saying he made off with
Ylucklucu and left Bantorra.
ユックユックを盗んでバントーラを飛び出たらしいぞ
Seriously? With a war-machine of the past?
まじかよ　追憶の戦機を…
Why did you do it?
どうしてなの？
If you can hear this, please answer me.
聞こえるなら返事をして
No, you must answer me!
いえ　返事をなさい
Volken Macmani!
ヴォルケン＝マクマーニ
Volken...
ヴォルケン
よかった
That's great.
I remember seeing it long ago...
今の一体…
昔見た　あれは　え…がお
A smile...
A young man who wanted nothing
more than to smile.
ただ笑いたかった少年
笑いたい
I want to smile.
Dam...
しまっ…
He killed out of his desire to smile.
笑顔になりたくて　人を殺めた
Thank you very much.
He killed out of his desire to smile.
Because all he wanted was to smile...
ただ笑いたかったから
お疲れ様…
Thank you very much.
He awaited the day when
he would finally smile.
あの日出会って笑顔を　届きたかったから
Thank you very much.
Qumola will probably
never smile again.
クモラは二度と笑わないだろう
嘘
No way.
Awesome!
すごーい
Awesome! Awesome! Just awesome!
すごい　すごい　すごい
Will you protect the world with me?
一緒に世界を守ってくれませんか？
Suicide? Were you trying to commit suicide?
自殺？　自殺しようとしていたんですか？
Yes.
そうだ
Why?
どうしてですか？
Are you going through a tough time?
なにか辛いことでもあったんですか？
と…とにかく
L-Listen!
You aren't going to preach to me that
suicide is bad, and I shouldn't do it, are you?
まさか　自殺はよくないからやめろとかいうんじゃないだろうな
Suicide is bad, and you shouldn't do it.
自殺はよくないから　やめたほうがいいと思います
I'm a killer.
俺は殺し続けて来たんだ
I've killed more than I can count.
もうこれ以上ないほどに　取り返しがつかないほどに
I can never atone for my sins.
殺す以外に方法はない
Killing me is the only way to help me!
There's another way.
I just haven't figured it out yet.
ありますよ　まだ分からないんですけど
Why are you smiling?
なぜ　笑う
クモラ
Qumola.
Thank you.
ありがとう
ノロティ
Noloty...
どっち？
Who are you now?
Don't cry sitting over me.
人の上で泣くな
涙はともかく　鼻水まで落ちてくる
I can handle the tears,
but your snot is dripping on me.
Enlike!
エンリケさん
邪魔だ　重い　退け
You're heavy and in the way. Move.
Looks like you got a new lease on life.
生き延びてしまいましたね
This isn't the time to smile. Stop.
笑ってる場合ではない　笑うな
You stop first.
エンリケさんこそ…
He longed to be with his mother.
母さんと一緒にいたかった
He didn't care if it was a lie,
if he had to throw everything away.
嘘でもいい　全てを捨ててもいい
All he wanted was to be held
against your chest once again.
ただ　もう一度あなたの胸に抱かれたかった
I'm back.
ただいま
Everyone needs to leave the labyrinth.
全員迷宮から出て行け　従わない者は殺す
I'll kill anyone who doesn't listen.
Mom!
母さん　大丈夫だった…
You did it for him.
それは彼のため
Are you okay? I shouldn't have left you alone!
You did it for him.
No, you did it for yourself.
いいえ　自分のため
I'm in pain, Mokkania...
You and he are one and the same.
彼は自分　自分は彼
Sorry! I'm so sorry, Mom!
You and he are one and the same.
I apologize for before.
先程は失礼いたしました　改めてご挨拶を
Allow me to properly introduce myself.
I am Winkeny Bizee of the Church
of Drowning in God's Grace.
神溺教団のウィンケニー＝ビゼと申します
母さん
Mom...
Two boys who lost their mothers.
母を失った　少年たち
ただいま
I'm back!
嘘をついて　人を殺して
I lied, I killed... I hated doing those things.
本当はいやだった
でも一緒にいたくて　忘れてた
But in my desire to be with her,
I forgot all of that.
そんな人じゃないのに
She wasn't that kind of person...
そんなことをしても喜ばないのに
She wouldn't approve of my behavior...
暴力はいけない
Violence is wrong.
強い者が弱い者を苛めてはいけない
The strong shouldn't bully the weak.
あの人を　殺してはいけない
I can't let her die.
What a dumb child.
馬鹿な子
No. He was happy.
いや　幸せそうだった
When he was first reunited with Renas,
he was genuinely happy.
レナスと会ったときの彼は本当に幸せそうだった
It's odd...
なぜだろう？
Just seeing the look of contentment
on his face made me...
なぜか　あの顔を見ることができただけで俺は…
That's it!
そうか
All I ever really wanted was to
reunite Mokkania with his mother.
俺はただモッカニアを母親と会わせてやりたかっただけだったんだ
名前は？
What's your name?
Hamyuts. Hamyuts Meseta.
ハミュッツ　ハミュッツ＝メセタ
What's yours?
あんなは？
Mattalast Balory, Armed Librarian.
マットアラスト＝バロリー　武装司書
ふんー　あんた　強い？
Are you strong?
Uh, I just told you I'm
an Armed Librarian.
武装司書って聞こえなかったか？
So? Are you stronger than me?
そんなこと　どうでもいい
あたしより　強い？
試してみ…
Care to find...
I knew it!
本当だ
Chacoly's a big fat liar.
やっぱりチャコリンは嘘ばっかりだ
There is someone stronger than me.
あたしより強い人いるじゃない？
I thought you were just a seamstress.
ただの針っ子かと思っていたね
Looks like I made a good friend, though.
どうやらいい友達になれそうだ
Friend? Stop that now.
友だち？　やめようよ
If I end up truly liking you,
the world will be destroyed.
私が本気であんたのこと好きになったら
この世界は滅ぶから
Huh?
ああ？
We should fight to the death.
殺し合うほうがいい
If you kill me,
あたしのこと殺したら
世界は救えるよ
the world might be saved.
Are you plotting something?
何か企んでいるのか？
World destruction, maybe?
世界の破滅かな
He's the top person in charge?
あれが一番偉い人？
Yeah. He's the revered
Acting Director Fotona.
まぁな　フォトナ館長代行様だ
But he looks so weak.
あんなに弱そうなのに？
やっぱりお前には分かるか？
You can tell, huh?
He's stronger than that old man,
さっきのお爺さんよりは強いけど
but give me a month and I could beat him.
一ヶ月もあれば倒せるかな
I'll pass you in six months, too.
マットも半年あれば追いぬけるよね
Me?
俺？
そのぐらいでしょう　マットって
That's about right for you,
wouldn't you say?
Hurry! Now!
急げ　早く
Yeah, I love it when it heats up.
かえて　熱くなるのが楽しみだね
The end already?
もう　おしまいか
Say, Matt?
ねぇ　マット
Hmm?
ん？
If no one out there can kill me,
もし　あたしを殺せる人誰もいなくなったら
will you do it, Matt?
マット殺してくれる？
You're okay with that?
いいのか？
ふん　やっぱ　いや
Actually, never mind!
Are you gonna kill me?
殺す　私　マットだけには殺されたくないな
You're the only person by whose
hands I don't want to die.
Long, long ago, over two
thousand years in the past,
遥か二千年もの昔
men spoke softly and were
satisfied with their lots in life.
人々は多くを語らず 足るを知り
互いに幸せに満ち溢れて暮していたと聞く
It is said they lived together in the
mutual pursuit of happiness.
It truly was the Age of Paradise.
それすなわち「楽園時代」
But the Gods left. The humans, alone,
remained to lament and grieve.
神々が去り
この世には嘆き悲しむ人間たちだけは残された
But they were ignorant of the fact
だが彼らは知らぬ
that Heaven still exists here on Earth!
天国は未だこの世に留まっていることを
我が名は楽園管理者
My name is the Governor of Paradise.
密かにその秘密を受け継ぐ者
I carry this secret with me.
Oh, me?
あら　あたしは？
I leave the rest to you.
後はよろしく
Much obliged.
心得た
幸福を
Happiness.
I can see it. I can see tomorrow.
私には見える
明日が見える
We have no one else who can
use telepathy at her level.
ミレポほどの「思考共有」の使い手はそういない
We can't afford to lose her right now.
今　あいつを失うわけにはいかない
But a fired-up Milepoc cannot be stopped.
でも　燃えるミレポは止められない
どうする？
So what should we do?
Those who dream...
求める者たち
思いを果たす者
Those whose dreams come true...
Those whose don't...
果たせぬ者
When it's all over, they all face
the same inevitable end.
いずれ　すべてに等しく終わりの時が訪れる
What? Shoot me.
どうした？　撃てよ
Freeze!
動かないで　動いたら　撃つわ
Move and I'll shoot.
No dice, missy.
You can't kill me with that.
駄目だよ　お嬢ちゃん　それじゃ勝てない
You'll have to attack me personally.
自分から攻めて来ないと
What?
何を？
You've never killed someone before, have you?
お前　人を殺したことないだろう
Damn.
くそ
It appears the stage is set.
舞台は整ったようだ
So it would seem.
そのようで
Do you think those two can reach you,
あの二人　君に辿り着くことができるかな
Lascall Othello?
ラスコール＝オセロ
Those girls are like precious gems.
宝石のような少女たちでございます
They just may be able to...
あるいは…
Despite all this, they continue in pursuit.
それでも　人が追い続ける
Until their last breath, they continue to pray.
命の限り願い続ける
夢を　幸福を　愛を
For their dreams, for happiness,
for love...
Thoughts become Books, living on forever.
思いは「本」となり　永遠に紡がれる
As do mine... For all time...
私の思いも　永遠に…
Taiyo tojiru mae ni
Hikari wo nakushite
Mekurumeku arashi nara
Temaneku mae ni tobikomu
Dare mo itsuka owaru no deshou
Sono hi ga kureba
Mawaridasu mirai wo mezashite
Tada sore wa mou shirusarete ita to shitemo
Sagashidasu kizutsuku imi sae kono te ni
Jibunrashiku aru tame ni
A Girl,
She knows.
きっと彼女は知っていた
She sees.
きっと彼女は見ていた
A Girl, a Girl,
She sees.
A weak victory
脆弱の勝利は敗北の証明
is proof of defeat.
A Girl, a Girl, and the Bed of God
少女与少女和神之睡铺
The girls are alike.
きっと彼女たちが　似ていた